Finding Aid for the Pan-American Exposition Sheet Music Collection, 1899-1909
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Pan-American Exposition Sheet Music Collection, 1899-1909
Mus. Arc. 8.2
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
1 box (36 items)
Thirty-five titles of sheet music related to the 1901 Pan-American Exposition in Buffalo and one title related to an exposition held in 1905 in Buffalo. All but nine of the titles are photocopies of works in the Buffalo & Erie County Public Library.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
Materials can be examined by qualified researchers in the Music Library during hours of operation during which Music Librarians are present. In order to insure access, researchers are advised to contact the Music Library in advance of visits.
Acquisition Information
The Buffalo & Erie County Library graciously loaned their collection of sheet music related to the Pan-American Exposition to the Music Library in 2001 in order to have preservation copies made and to have the music digitized. Other titles came from other sources, including the University Archives and individual donors, Brenda Battleson, Kerry Grant, and John Bewley.
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Alternate Forms
All of the titles in the collection have been digitized. They are available online at: Sheet Music of the Pan-American Exposition, part of the University Libraries exhibit, Illuminations: Revisiting the Buffalo Pan-American Exposition of 1901.
Historical Note
The Pan-American Exposition held in Buffalo in 1901 was one of a series of world expositions that were mounted at the end of the 19th century and the beginning of the 20th century, including the 1876 Centennial Exposition in Philadelphia, the Paris Exposition in 1889, the Columbian Exposition of 1893 in Chicago, and the Louisiana Purchase Exposition held in St. Louis in 1904. Like the other expositions, the Pan-American provided an opportunity to showcase the latest developments in technology and industries. It also provided a showcase for the arts, including music. Most of the musical display was in the form of performance, be it by renowned bands like those of John Philip Sousa or Thomas Preston Brooke, or by any of the seventy-one organists who performed on the Emmons Howard organ installed in the Temple of Music.
Music composed for the Exposition was predominantly in the form of popular pieces that drew on the celebrity of the event in order to sell music. For this reason, most of the music is ephemeral in nature, much like other Exposition memorabilia. Music that stands out is that composed by John Philip Sousa and the other band leaders who performed at the Exposition, Thomas Preston Brooke (Chicago Marine Band) and Francesco Fanciulli (71st Regiment Band). Victor Herbert, who conducted the Pittsburgh Orchestra at the Exposition, composed his PanAmericana especially for the Exposition and it reputedly won a gold medal for composition, though no record of any other entrants exists. The assassination of President William McKinley at the Exposition was also memorialized in music.
Sheet music at the turn of the century was still prevalently issued in a larger format with illustrated title pages. The illustrations include portraits of band leaders and dignitaries, views of Exposition buildings and scenes, and general boosterism for the Exposition and the city of Buffalo.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains thirty-five pieces of music, thirty-four of which are related to the Pan-American Exposition. The one exception is a work written for the Exposition held in Buffalo in the summer of 1909. Nine of the pieces are in original form; 26 are photocopies. There are songs in the collection and works for solo piano (some of the marches were also available in arrangement for band). There are also works in the collection that commemorate the death of President McKinley.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in one series.
Container List
- Anderson, Edward D., composer Pan-American march: Buffalo, 1901 Washington, D.C.: Sanders and Stayman 1899, 5 p. of music: col. ill.; 37 cm. Photocopy (Box 1, Item 1)
  Title page illustration: photograph of bison over map of the Americas.
  For piano.
- Austin, B. P. Pan-American: march: op. 195 Hammondsport, N.Y.: Hammondsport Music Co., 1901, 5 p. of music: col. ill.; 35 cm. Photocopy (Box 1, Item 2)
  Title page illustration: inset drawing of the Pan-American Exposition’s United States Government Building on red, white, and blue background.
  For band and orchestra; arranged for piano.
- Austin, James H., composer Pan-American: march and two-step New York: Richard A. Saalfield, 1901, [3] p. of music: col. ill.; 37 cm. Photocopy (Box 1, Item 3)
  Title page illustration: drawing of North and South America shaking hands, symbolized by George Washington and Simón Bolívar.
- Bradley, D. F., composer Pan-American march: for piano: op. 44 Utica, N.Y.: D.F. Bradley, 1901, 5 p. of music; 36 cm. (Box 1, Item 4)
- Brooke, Thomas Preston, 1856-1921 Buffalo march: for the piano Cincinnati: John Church Company, 1901, 5 p. of music: ill.; 32 cm. Photocopy (Box 1, Item 5)
  Title page illustration: bandmaster Thomas Preston Brooke; a buffalo jumping through the letter B in the title.
- Dillon, John, composer Put me off at Buffalo: the one and only Buffalo song New York: M. Witmark and Sons, 1895, [5] p. of music: col. ill.; 34 cm. Photocopy (Box 1, Item 6)
  Title page illustration: Caricatures of an African, an Arab, a Native American, an East Asian, and a frontiersman.
  For medium voice and piano.
  Words by Harry Dillon
- Douglas, Theo., composer At the Pan-American Fair: in 1901 [Buffalo, N.Y.?] (45 Division St.): Graser Bros., 1899, 1 score ([16] p.); 36 cm. (Box 1, Item 7)
  Songs for voice and piano.
  With: Two boys in blue / [music] by Erwin C. Koeppen
- Edwards, Estelle Pan-American: characteristic march and two-step Baltimore, Md.: Cohen and Hughes, 1901, 5, [1] p. of music: col. ill.; 35 cm. Photocopy (Box 1, Item 8)
  Title page illustration: drawing of Native American holding globe in which title is set / Rickert.
- Edwards, Gus, 1879-1945 Pan, Pan, Pan New York: Howley, Haviland and Dresser, 1901, 1 score ([8] p.): col. ill.; 35 cm. Photocopy (Box 1, Item 9)
  Title page illustration: drawing of three ladies and two gentlemen walking towards Pan-American Exposition grounds. Small photographic portraits of the composer and lyricist at bottom of page.
  Song for medium voice and piano.
  Words by Will. D. Cobb
- Evans, H. Geo. Pan-American Exposition march: two-step, op. 29; D.M.V. march: two step, op. 28 Johnstown, Pa.: Pepper-Evans Music Co., 1901, [6] p. of music: ill.; 36 cm. (Box 1, Item 10)
  Title page illustration (1st work): inset photo. of H. Geo. Evans.
- Fanciulli, F. (Francesco), 1853-1915 Electric century: march and two step New York: W. Paris Chambers, 1901, 6 p. of music: col. ill.; 36 cm. (Box 1, Item 11)
  Title page illustration: the Electric Tower at the 1901 Pan-American Exposition set over an American flag.
- Fearis, J. S. (John Sylvester), 1867-1932 Beautiful isle of somewhere Chicago: Forster Music, 1901, 1897, 1 score (5, [1] p.): ill.; 31 cm. (Box 1, Item 12)
  "As sung at the funeral of our martyred President William McKinley by the Euterpean Quartette." Cover illustration: Inset photographs of President McKinley by Courtney Studio, Canton, Oh., and the members of the Euterpean Quartette: Harriet Levinger, Fannie Levinger, Jeanette Bauhof, and Katherine Baehrens. Decorative lithography by Falk and Co., Chicago.
  For soprano voice and piano or organ.
  Words by Jessie Brown Pounds
- Gethoefer, Ida A. Pan-American Exposition: three step Buffalo, N.Y. (269 Main St.): Denton, Cottier and Daniels, 1898, 5 p. of music: col. ill.; 37 cm. Photocopy (Box 1, Item 13)
  Title page illustration: drawing of head of Native American set within a frying pan.
- Hartenstine, W. Franklin Exposition march and two step: 1901, Buffalo, N.Y. Buffalo, N.Y.: Denton, Cottier and Daniels, 1900, 5 p. of music: col. ill.; 35 cm. Photocopy (Box 1, Item 14)
  Title page illustration: the official medallion logo of the 1901 Pan-American Exposition, by Raphael Beck.
- Haussauer, Meranda H. Pan-American waltz Buffalo, N.Y. (217 Virginia St.): J.S. and M.H. Haussauer, 1899, [3] p. of music: col. ill.; 35 cm. Photocopy (Box 1, Item 15)
  Title page illustration: map of the Americas.
- Hedger, Harry D., Mrs. Our country's loss Boston: Mrs. Harry D. Hedger, 1902, 1 score (5 p.): ill.; 34 cm. Photocopy (Box 1, Item 16)
  Title page illustration: photograph of President William McKinley set between two U.S. flags and a photograph of Mrs. Harry D. Hedger, captioned "First lady cycle rider in the U.S.A."
  For solo voice, chorus (SATB), and piano.
  Words by the composer
- Herbert, Victor, 1859-1924 Panamericana: morceau characteristique New York: M. Witmark and Sons, 1901, [6] p. of music: ill.; 35 cm. (Box 1, Item 17)
  Title page illustration: illuminated grounds of the 1901 Pan-American Exposition at night.
- Klock, Homer R. S. Pan-American: two step and march of 1901 Stamford, Conn.: Homer R.S. Klock, 1900, 5, [1] p. of music; 36 cm. (Box 1, Item 18)
- Kohn, Milton H. Hymn New York: Vandersloot Music Co., 1901, 1 score (5, [1] p.): ill.; 28 cm. Photocopy (Box 1, Item 19)
  Title page illustration: drawing of William S. McKinley / A.J. Dewey.
  Words by the composer.
- Lincoln, Harry J., 1878-1937 McKinley's memorial march: in memory of our late beloved President Williamsport, Pa.: United States Music Co., 1901, 5, [1] p. of music: ill.; 36 cm. (Box 1, Item 20)
  Title page illustration: photograph of William S. McKinley.
- Liné, Hans S. Pan-American Exposition march and two-step Chicago: Windsor Music Co., 1901, [5] p. of music: ill.; 37 cm. (Box 1, Item 21)
  Title page illustration: drawings of the Albright-Knox Art Gallery and two buildings from the 1901 Pan-American Exposition in Buffalo: the U.S. Government Building and the Service Building.
- Loraine, William, b. 1869 Trip to Buffalo: a musical extravaganza. Maidie, come be my lady New York: M. Witmark and Sons, 1901, 1 score (5, [1] p.): col. ill.; 31 cm. Photocopy (Box 1, Item 22)
  Title page illustration: gondolas on canal at the 1901 Pan-American Exposition in Buffalo, with the Exposition grounds in the background.
  Words by Harry B. Marshall
- Loraine, William, b. 1869 Trip to Buffalo: a musical extravaganza. In Buffalo New York: M. Witmark and Sons, 1901, 1 score (5, [1] p.): col. ill.; 31 cm. Photocopy (Box 1, Item 23)
- Loraine, William, b. 1869 A trip to Buffalo: a musical extravaganza. An oriental maid New York: M. Witmark and Sons, 1901, 1 score (5, [1] p.): col. ill.; 31 cm. Photocopy (Box 1, Item 24)
  Song for high voice and piano.
- President Wm. McKinley's favorite hymns: words and music Chicago: Edwards Deutsch and Heitmann, 1901, 1 score ([2] p.): ill.; 35 cm. (Box 1, Item 25)
  Contains Nearer my God to Thee / [words by] Sarah F. Adams; [music by] Dr. Lowell Mason -- Lead kindly Light / [words by] John H. Newman; [music by] John B. Dykes. Title page illustration: portrait of President William McKinley set inside wreath, below eagle holding U.S. banner.
- Near, Myron Fowler Hurrah! for Buffalo 1901: souvenir song Buffalo, N.Y. (269 Main St.): Denton, Cottier and Daniels 1901, 1 score (3 p.): ill.; 31 cm. Photocopy (Box 1, Item 26)
  Title page illustration: small images of Niagara Falls, a buffalo head, and the Electric Tower at the Pan-American Exposition.
- Ralph, E. B. Pan-American Exposition march and two-step Buffalo, N.Y. (269 Main St.): Denton, Cottier and Daniels, 1898, 5 p. of music: ill.; 32 cm. (Box 1, Item 27)
  Title page illustration: inset photographs of J.M. Brinker and Fred C.M. Lautz.
- Ryder, Fred L. March of the buffaloes: two-step Chicago: McKinley Music, 1901, [4] p. of music: ill.; 35 cm. (Box 1, Item 28)
  Cover illustration: a herd of buffalo.
- Schultz, Herman E. Buffalo means business: song / words by Walter H. Cluxton; music by Herman E. Schultz Buffalo, N.Y.: Celebrity Music Co., 1909, 1 score (5, [1] p.): col. ill.; 36 cm. (Box 1, Item 29)
  Title page illustration: drawing of lady’s head in profile, by M. Wilson Craig.
  Words by Walter H. Cluxton.
  This item postdates the Pan-American Exposition so was not digitized for the University Libraries exhibition. The photocopy is missing page 4.
- Schwartz, Jean, 1878-1956 Don't put me off at Buffalo any more New York: Shapiro, Bernstein, and von Tilzer, 1901, 1 score (5, [1] p.): col. ill.; 33 cm. Photocopy (Box 1, Item 30)
  Title page illustration: four scenes depicted in the song, two scenes of the 1901 Pan-American Exposition in Buffalo, and a photographic portrait of Maude Nugent.
  Words by William Jerome.
- Sousa, John Philip, 1854-1932 Invincible eagle march Cincinnati: John Church Company, 1901, 5 p. of music: port.; 35 cm. (Box 1, Item 31)
  Title page illustration: portrait of Sousa.
  Originally for band; arranged for piano.
- Von Tilzer, Harry, 1872-1946 Are you a buffalo? New York: Shapiro, Bernstein and von Tilzer, 1901, 1 score (5, [1] p.): col. ill.; 36 cm. Photocopy (Box 1, Item 32)
  Library has one copy of music, with two different versions of cover. Title page illustration on 2nd copy: photograph of Lew Dockstader in blackface set within frame formed by four buffalo heads and a Native American headress.
  Song for voice and piano.
  Words by Edward P. Moran
- Weiler, Harry J. Pan-American cake walk: 1901: grand characteristic march and 2 step Buffalo, N.Y.: Harry J. Weiler, 1900, 5 p. of music: col. ill.; 35 cm. Photocopy (Box 1, Item 33)
  Title page illustration: a buffalo set within a frying pan.
- Weldon, A. F. (Alfred F.), 1862-1914 From Mexico to Buffalo: march Chicago, Ill.: N. Nelson, 1901, 5 p. of music: col. ill.; 36 cm. (Box 1, Item 34)
  Title page illustration: oval photographs of the Castle of Chapultepec, the National Palace, City of Mexico, and Francisco E. Lacroix, in setting with Mexican and United States flags.
  For piano; also available for band.
- Wright, E. R., composer Pan-American march and two-step Fargo, N.D.: Stones Music House, 1900, 5, [1] p. of music: col. ill.; 32 cm. (Box 1, Item 35)
  Title page illustration: photograph of the composer(?) set within a blue and gold ribbon, with caption: Seal of success.
- Bendix, Theo. (Theodore) A trip to Buffalo: descriptive New York: M. Witmark & Sons, 1901, 1 score (7, [1] p.): col. ill.; 36 cm. (Box 1, Item 36)
  Title page illustration: illustration of a traveler arriving at the Pan American Exposition of 1901 in Buffalo, New York, in green, white, and black.
  For voice and piano.
Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog.
Subjects
Songs with piano; Marches; Piano music; Piano music, Arranged; Pan-American Exposition (1901: Buffalo, N.Y.)--Songs and music; McKinley, William, 1843-1901--Assassination--Songs and music
Genres
Sheet music
Associated Material
Additional Guides
All scores in the collection are cataloged in WorldCat and are available in BISON, the online catalog for the University at Buffalo Libraries, by performing a "Title begins with" search under "Pan American Exposition Sheet Music Collection".
Related Resources
Finding Aid for the Music Images from the Pan-American Exposition, Buffalo, 1901
Mus. Arc. 8
The images in this collection include scenes of music venues at the Pan-American Exposition held in Buffalo in 1901, including the Temple of Music, the Midway, and bandstands. The collection also contains images of musicians who performed at the Exposition and musical instruments used at the Exposition.
Music and Musicians at the Pan-American Exposition
Music portion of the larger exhibition, Illuminations: Revisiting the Buffalo Pan-American Exposition of 1901.